A Guide to the Letters of E. E. Cummings and Marion Cummings, 1942-1960
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Letters of E. E. Cummings and Marion Cummings, 1942-1960
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6246-I
This collection consists of 17 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from David J. Holmes on 1999 November 29.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of letters to the writer Lloyd Frankenberg and his wife, the painter, Loren MacIver. Topics include Marion Cummings' health, a Guggenheim fellowship, cummings' art, and life at Silver Lake (N.H.). One letter contains nonsensical references to "The Enormous Room" and Joseph F. Gould.
With the letters is a catalog for an exhibition of paintings by E.E. Cummings at the American British Art Center, N.Y.
Contents List
- Carbon typescript of the "Foreword" to the American British Art Center Catalog of an Exhibition of Paintings by E.E. Cummings, written by Cummings [1944], TMs, 1p.
- Letters & Notes
  - E.E. Cummings to Lloyd Frankenberg and Loren MacIver 1942 Jul 2, TLS, 1p. With envelope.
    Makes nonsensical references to his book The Enormous Room and Joseph Ferdinand Gould (1889-1957), "probably, You Enormous Room Man, there exist secret passages among those closets or better interstices; and surely the former will end with a fur lined trapdoor which (being lifted) reveals a colossal green candy box which (being opened) reveals a microscopic mahogany roll top desk which (via dynamite) reveals a life statured nugget of thoroughly once chewing gum containing at its very most exact centre Joe ('Are You Plunderable?') Gould Inc disguised as a Moslem piano tuner."
  - E.E. Cummings to Loren MacIver [1944 Feb 4], TLS, 1p. With envelope.
    Gives advice about the best type of mattress for someone with back trouble, recommends Dr. Ober for a physician, and discusses the health problems (diagnosed as rheumatoid arthritis) and gold injection treatments of his wife, Marion Morehouse Cummings (1906-1969); he also refers to his painting and his need for canvas.
  - E.E. Cummings to Loren MacIver [ca. 1944?], TNS, 1p.
    In this note accompanying a carbon of his typescript "Foreword" (described under Manuscripts above) he writes, "since the wily cataloguesters wouldn't let you write about my paintings, will you graciously accept this unworthy substitute with our unhero's deep apologies and best wishes?"
  - E.E. Cummings to Loren MacIver [1945 Sep 6], APC
    An unsigned postcard addressed to Loren, containing only the words "merci bien" written out by the poet in letters which increase in size from left to right.
  - E.E. Cummings to Lloyd Frankenberg 1945 Oct 8, ANS, 1p. With envelope.
    Thanks Lloyd for his opinion of his book One Times One saying, "only a poet could pay me the supreme compliment of recognizing in 1 x 1, not a book but a human being.
  - E.E. Cummings to Loren MacIver 1946 Jun 19, APCS
    Expresses his delight that she approves of the photostats and invites Loren and Lloyd to come up and spend a week with them in July or August.
  - E.E. Cummings to Lloyd Frankenberg and Loren MacIver n.d., AN
    Several brief miscellaneous notes written by Cummings in pencil, on odd bits of paper, one on a typed letter from a representative of the American British Art Center to Cummings.
  - Marion Cummings to Lloyd Frankenberg and Loren MacIver 1940 Apr 2, ALS, 2p. With envelope.
    Congratulates them on the receipt of the Guggenheim Fellowship.
  - Marion Cummings to Loren MacIver [1944 Aug 16], ANS, 2p. With envelope.
    Asks Loren if she can ship a head of garlic to them at Silver Lake, New Hampshire, since "the food situation is bad here & food pretty monotonous."
  - Marion Cummings to Loren MacIver 1945 Jul 4, ALS, 2p. With envelope.
    Sends some sweaters to Loren for the coming winter and discusses the art show of E.E. Cumming in Rochester, "Cummings show was beautifully hung & looked fine & five pictures have been sold."
  - Marion Cummings to Loren MacIver 1945 Aug 30, ALS, 2p.With envelope.
    Thanks her for sending garlic to them in New Hampshire and describes her natural surroundings, "Our mountains are still beautiful & though the flowers are almost gone & the birds are migrating we still have deer. At noon today, I happened to look out the window & there about 50 feet away in the bright sunlight & standing in tall grass was a beautiful buck. Cummings was even nearer to him though obscured by some bushes, and was writing in his notebook."
  - Marion Cummings to Loren MacIver [1946 Sep 22], ANS, 1p. With envelope.
    Writes "Here are some leaves & they will be followed by us in a few days."
  - Marion Cummings to Lloyd Frankenberg 1947 Sep 25, APCS
    On a postcard with a scene from Silver Lake, New Hampshire Marion mentions "the birds are getting on the wing, where it couldn't be any colder than it is on the ground."
  - Marion Cummings to Lloyd Frankenberg and Loren MacIver [1956 Apr 7], APCS
    On a postcard featuring the Grand Cafí Restaurant, Saint Marks Square, Venice, Italy, Marion says they "drove the caretakers crazy trying to find your swallows. There are none."
  - Marion Cummings to Loren MacIver 1960 Aug 2, ALS, 3p. With envelope.
    Sends a color photograph of MacIver's painting (not present), mentions her husband "Cummings is well and working hard, painting, writing, feeding his various birds & animals and being glad that he's here" and describes the antics of a local Yellow Bellied Sapsucker in their yard.
- Catalog for an Exhibition of Paintings by E.E. Cummings at the American British Art Center, New York, with small pencil drawing of a coffee pot and mug 1944, print